Finding Aid for Vice President for Student Affairs (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library
- Henry Johnson, Vice-President of Student Services, 1950-1985; 1972-1985
  - Topical Files
    - University Health Services
      - Reports
        - A Survey of Knowledge, Attitudes and Beliefs about Pertinent Health Issues Among U of M Students Living in the Residence Halls, 1988 (Box 35)
      - Sexually Transmitted Diseases, 1988 (Box 35)
      - Unit Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 35)
      - Venereal Disease Clinic
        - Contract, 1976 (Box 35)
        - Evaluations (of clinic), circa 1976 (Box 35)
      - Wellness Program, 1987 (Box 35)
    - University Judiciary System
      - Resolutions and History, 1971-1979 (Box 35)
      - Unified Manual of the Student Judicial System, 1971 (Box 35)
    - University of Michigan, Dearborn, 1982-1986 (Box 35)
    - Values and Attitudes, 1964 (Box 35)
    - Vice Provost for Information Technology, 1983-1985 (Box 35)
    - Volunteers for International Hospitality Programs 1972, 1988 (includes annual report and constitution) (Box 35)
    - Washtenaw County Legal Aid Society, 1970-1977 (Box 35)
      (See Also-Legal Services, Student)
    - William Monroe Trotter House
      - General, 1972-1989 (Box 35)
      - Activity Reports, 1982-1989 (Box 35)
      - Budget, 1973-1989; 2 folders (Box 35)
      - Goals, 1973, 1981 (Box 35)
      - History, 1972-1975 (Box 35)
      - Housing Facilities Condition Audit, 1989 (Box 35)
      - Programs, circa 1972 (Box 35)
      - Report
        - Report of the Task Force to Study Wm. Trotter House Direction, circa 1979 (Box 35)
      - Year End Evaluation, 1989 (Box 35)
    - Wilson, Dr. Roselle (Assistant to the V.P. for Student Services), 1979-1985 (Box 35)
    - Women
      - General (includes Women in Higher Administration Strategies for Change, 1979), 1974-1986 (Box 35)
      - Catalyst Program, 1964 (Box 35)
      - Women and Minority Services
        - General, 1977 (Box 35)
        - Central Coordinating Committee (minutes), 1979 (Box 35)
      - Women's Advocate, Office of (includes partial listing of student women's organizations), 1972-1974 (Box 35)
      - Women's Career Fair, 1977 (Box 35)
      - Women's Studies, 1972-1973 (Box 35)
    - WUOM, 1986-1988 (Box 35)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Works series (2.5 linear feet) consists of Brochures, Calendars, Directories, Manuals, Newsletters and Regulations generated by the Office for Student Affairs. Annual Reports and printed materials for sub-units are found in the printed catalog at the Bentley Historical Library under the name University of Michigan followed by the name of the unit.
  - Unit Publications
    - Annual Reports
      - reports, 1972 - 1984 (Box 37)
      - reports, 1994-1996 (Box 37)
    - Brochures
      - Student Activities Building, undated, including history of building (Box 35)
      - Undergraduate Education: Class of 1994 (Box 35)
    - Calendars
      - Poor Student's Almanac, 1971-1972 (Box 35)
    - Directories
      - Who's Who in Student Services: A Staff Directory (Box 35)
        - 1978-1979
    - Manuals
      - Design for Living: A Philosophy of Growth and Development at Michigan, 1963 (Box 35)
      - University Mentorship Program, 1991-1992 (Box 35)
    - Newsletters
      - Campus Comment, 1969-1971 (Box 35)
      - Family Matters, 1995-2005
        - 1995 (Box 35)
        - Family Matters, 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 37)
        - 1996-1999 (Box 43)
        - 2000-2005 (Box 43)
      - O.S.S. Soundings, 1979-1980 (Box 35)
      - Voices, 1993 (Box 35)
    - Regulations
      - The Administrative Code of the Student Automobile Regulations, 1961 (Box 35)
      - Code of Student Conduct, 1996 (Box 35)
      - Standards for Students, 1965-1966 (Box 35)
      - University Regulations, undated (Box 35)
      - University Regulations Concerning Student Organizations, 1961 (Box 35)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    - Judicial Board
      - Manuals
        - Judicial Board Training Manual, 1993 (Box 35)
    - Office of Student Programs
      - Brochures, undated (Box 35)
    - University Mentorship Program
      - Brochures, undated (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials
    - A Student Affair, 1998-1999 (Box 37)
    - Alternatives for University Involvement in Child Care (Box 37)
    - Binge Drinking Committee, 1999 (Box 37)
    - Brochures, undated (Box 37)
    - Committee to Study Advocacy, 1975 (Box 37)
    - Community Services - Brochures and Archival Reports (Box 37)
    - Counseling and Psychological Services (Box 37)
    - Counseling Services (Box 37)
    - Delphi Issues for the 80s (Box 37)
    - Disabled Student Services (Box 37)
    - Division of Student Affairs - General (Box 37)
    - Entering Student Survey, 1993-2003; 2006 (Box 37)
    - Expect Respect Campaign (Box 37)
    - Housing Division (Box 37)
    - Invitations (Box 37)
    - Judicial Board Training Manual, 1993 (Box 37)
    - Lesbian Gay Bisexual Programs Office (Box 37)
    - Living-Learning Programs Task Force, 1996 (Box 37)
    - Management of Objectives Handbook (Box 37)
    - Manual: Design for Living, 1963 (Box 37)
    - Mediation Services (Box 37)
    - Minority Counseling and Information (Box 37)
    - Newsletters
      - Campus Comment, 1969-1971 (Box 37)
      - The Community Focus, 1994; 2000-2002 (Box 37)
      - Issues Updates (Box 37)
      - O.S.S. Soundings, 1979-1980 (Box 37)
      - Voices, 1993-1994 (Box 37)
    - Office of Program Analysis - The Central Area Residence Environment as Perceived by its Residents, 1980 (Box 37)
    - Office of Student Services - General (Box 37)
    - Rackham Graduate School (Box 37)
    - Regulations
      - The Administrative Code of the Student Automobile Regulations, 1961 (Box 43)
      - Code of Student Conduct, 1996 (Box 43)
      - Standards for Students (Box 43)
      - Statement of Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1992 (Box 43)
      - Student Policy on Alcohol and Other Drugs (Box 43)
      - University Policies Affecting Students, 1998; 2003 (Box 43)
      - University Regulations, undated (Box 43)
      - University Regulations Concerning Student Affairs, Conduct, and Discipline, 1949; 1951; 1954-1956; 1959 (Box 43)
      - University Regulations Concerning Student Conduct, 1962 (Box 43)
      - University Regulations Concerning Student Organizations, 1961 (Box 43)
      - University Rules... on the Use and Possession of Firearms and Other Dangerous Weapons, 1970 (Box 43)
    - School of Education (Box 43)
    - Senior Day, 1994-1998 (Box 43)
    - Student Fees and Fee Regulations (Box 43)
    - Student Organization Programming (Box 43)
    - The Undergraduate Experience Surveys (Box 43)
    - University Diversity (Box 43)
    - University Mentorship Program, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - What's on Our Students' Minds, undated; 2004-2007 (Box 43)
    - Who's Who in Student Services: A Staff Directory, 1978-1979 (Box 43)
- Topical Files
  Two alphabetically arrange Topical Files spanning the tenures of several vice-presidents have been received in various accessions. They cover the years 1960-1991 (received in 1993 accession) and 1953-1995 (received in 1994-1998 accessions.)
  - Topical Files, 1960-1991
    The Topical Files, 1960-1991, (.8 linear feet) are alphabetically arranged, covering the period 1960-1991. It was received as separate accession in 1993 and includes material from the tenures of James A. Lewis, Richard L. Cutler, Barbara W. Newell, Robert L. Knauss, Henry Johnson, Mary Ann Swain and Maureen Hartford. The records from the tenure of Henry Johnson appear to parallel those of the Henry johns series (1989-1991 accession.) The researcher should therefore consult both series to find all materials on a given topic. The "Operations Reports, 1988-1989" are of interest, as they are indicative of the purpose and goals of the various sub-units.
    The researcher should consult the Bentley Historical Library's manuscript catalog for descriptions of other University of Michigan collections related to student life, including those described in the History section of the finding aid.
    - Bureau of Psychological Services (Opinion Attitude Interest Survey), 1960-1967 (Box 38)
    - Campus Safety Committee, 1990 (Box 38)
    - Career Counseling, 1968 (Box 38)
    - Constituency Advocates, 1972-1973 (Box 38)
    - Correspondence (outgoing), 1990-1991 (Box 38)
    - Education Innovation Advocate (EIA), 1974 (Box 38)
    - Evaluation Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 38)
    - Goals and Objectives, 1990 (Box 38)
    - Guild House, 1978-1980 (Box 38)
    - Historical Materials, 1977-79 (Box 38)
    - Housing (staff concerns), 1969 (Box 38)
    - Michigan Student Assembly (MSA) (history), 1976 (Box 38)
    - Michigan Union
      - General, 1989-1991 (Box 38)
      - Budget, 1990-1992 (Box 38)
      - September Incident (re: student social events), 1991 (Box 38)
    - Michigan Union Grill (MUG), 1990-1991 (Box 38)
    - Newsletter Task Force, 1979-1980
    - Occupational Safety, 1970-1977 (Box 38)
    - Office of Special Services and Programs (OSSP), 1971-1975 (Box 38)
    - Ombudsman (proposal for), 1970-1972 (Box 38)
    - Operations Reports, 1988-1989
      - Campus Information Center (Box 38)
      - Career Planning and Placement (Box 38)
      - Counseling Services (Box 38)
      - Housing, 3 folders (Box 38)
      - International Center (Box 38)
      - Ombudsman (monthly case load statistics) (Box 38)
      - University Health Services (Box 38)
    - Pass-it-On Freedom School, 1972 (Box 38)
    - Pendleton Library, 1971 (Box 38)
    - Publications Listing, 1971; 1973 (Box 38)
    - Reports
      - A Guide to Information Sources at University of Michigan, 1977 (Box 38)
      - Michigan Union/North Campus Commons Organizational Assessment, 1989 (Box 38)
      - Residence Hall Based Academic Counseling Program, 1974 (Box 38)
      - Report on Northwood V Project, undated (Box 38)
    - Research (current and recent), undated (Box 38)
    - Residence Hall Survey, 1969; 1974 (Box 38)
    - Resource and Development Committee (minutes), 1974-1975 (Box 38)
    - Staff, 1990-1991 (Box 38)
    - Staff Development, 1990-1991 (Box 38)
    - Statement of Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1992 (Box 38)
    - Student Organizational Services (includes minutes), 1976 (Box 38)
    - Student Organizations Coalition, 1974 (Box 38)
    - Swain, Mary Ann (Vice President for Academic Affairs), 1989-1990 (Box 38)
    - Thursday Night Coalition, 1973 (Box 38)
  - Topical Files, 1953-1995
    The alphabetically arranged Topical Files, 1953-1995 (2 linear feet) were received in the several accessions from 1994-1998. The early years of this file document two activities, Michigras, a spring carnival and J-Hop a dance. These activities were supervised by Maurice Rinkel, the auditor of Student Organizations in the Office of Student Programs. A significant piece of the early 1970s documents are the records of the Ann Arbor Community Coalition. The coalition was the umbrella organization for four different programs, the Black Caucus Against Drugs, the Community Center Project, Drug Help and the OSS Drug Education Project. There were several reports made about the status of the drug problem in Ann Arbor by Herbert Wong and Thomas Greenfield, which the records contain. Of interest in the latter years covered by the records are several folders which contain papers from student groups that were campaigning for minority rights in the early 1990s. Mary Ann Swain's interim position as Vice President of Student Affairs is documented within the record group.
    - Academic Affairs Advisory Council, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Academic Programming Group, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Academic Services Board, 1992-1995 (Box 39)
    - Advertising Information Center, 1969-1974 (Box 39)
    - Africenergy, 1991-1992 (Box 39)
    - Alliance for Undergraduate Education, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Alumni Center, 1991-1992 (Box 39)
    - Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA)
      - Minutes, 1992 (Box 39)
      - Memoranda, 1992 (Box 39)
      - Reports, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Ann Arbor Community Coalition
      - By-laws, circa 1970 (Box 39)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 39)
      - Financial, 1971-1975 (Box 39)
      - Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 39)
      - Miscellaneous Administrative, 1971-1973 (Box 39)
      - Proposal
        - circa 1971-1974 (Box 39)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 39)
      - Report by H. Wong and T. Greenfield
        - 1972-1977 (Box 39)
        - 1975 (Box 39)
    - Black Students Union (BSU) and Progressive People of Color, 1990-1991 (Box 39)
    - Bob Dylan-The Band Concert, 1974 (Box 39)
    - Career Planning and Placement, 1977-1995 (Box 39)
    - Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (CAAS), 1987-1990 (Box 39)
    - Center for the Education of Women (CEW), 1992-1995 (Box 39)
    - Chief Student Affairs Officers (CSAO), 1988-1991 (Box 39)
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation, 1991 (Box 39)
    - Counseling Services, 1988-1991 (Box 39)
    - Council on Academic and Student Affairs, 1990-1991 (Box 39)
    - Deputization, 1991-1992 (Box 39)
    - Ethics and Religion, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Foreign Student Insurance
      - 1974-1992 (Box 39)
      - 1993 (Box 39)
    - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA), 1990-1992 (Box 39)
    - Global College, 1992 (Box 39)
    - Health Services
      - 1990-1995 (Box 39)
      - Memoranda, 1990-1995 (Box 39)
    - Housing, 1990 (Box 39)
    - Housing Task Force, 1980-1990 (Box 40)
    - Intergroup Relations and Conflict Program, 1991-1992 (Box 40)
    - International Center
      - Memoranda, 1989-1994 (Box 40)
      - Reports, 1969-1991 (Box 40)
    - J-Hop, 1954-1956 (Box 40)
    - KUUMBA, 1991-1992 (Box 40)
    - Legislation, 1973-1977 (Box 40)
    - Lesbian and Gay Men's Rights Organizing Committee (LaGroc), 1988-1990 (Box 40)
    - Libraries, 1977-1990 (Box 40)
    - Major Events Advisory Task Force, 1990-1991 (Box 40)
    - Michigan Advertising Works (MAW), 1973-1975 (Box 40)
    - Michigan Union Affirmative Action, 1979-1981 (Box 40)
    - Michigan Campus Compact, 1992-1993 (Box 40)
    - Michigras
      - 1953-1954 (Box 40)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 40)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 40)
      - 1958-1960 (Box 40)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 40)
    - Minority Affairs Commission, 1990-1991 (Box 40)
    - Miscellaneous Student Activities, 1965-1978 (Box 40)
    - M-Quality, 1994 (Box 40)
    - Multiculturalism, 1993-1994 (Box 40)
    - North Campus Commons (NCC), 1990-1991 (Box 40)
    - Occupational Safety, 1976 (Box 40)
    - Office of Financial Aid, 1993-1994 (Box 40)
    - Office of Student Programs, 1954-1980 (Box 40)
    - Office of Student Programs, Gary Smith, 1978-1979 (Box 40)
    - People of Color Against the War and Racism, 1991 (Box 40)
    - Political Correctness, 1991 (Box 40)
    - Senior Leadership Team, 1991 (Box 40)
    - Socially Active Latino Student Union (SALSA), 1992 (Box 40)
    - Spring Weekend, 1954-1963 (Box 40)
    - Student Organization Development Center (SODC), 1988-1992 (Box 40)
    - Student Relations Committee
      - Correspondence, 1989-1992 (Box 40)
      - Minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 40)
    - Student Right Commission, 1991 (Box 40)
    - United Coalition Against Racism (UCAR), 1989-1990 (Box 40)
    - Universal Identification Card System (MCARD), 1992-1995 (Box 40)
    - University Mentorship Program, 1991-1992 (Box 40)
    - University Musical Society, 1992 (Box 40)
    - West Point Class Trip, 1955-1956 (Box 40)
- Mary Ann Swain and Maureen Hartford, 1990-2005
  The accession is comprised of the series Mary Ann Swain/Maureen Hartford, 1990-2005 (2 linear feet) was received as part of a 2002 accession with an addition made in 2013. The series includes records associated with campus improvement, classes, DSA Strategic Data Planning, experiences of women students, First Year Experience, health benefits, Leadership 2017 Program, campus safety, sexual orientation, surveys, and the undergraduate education statement. The records on campus improvement deal with various projects meant to improve the lives of students at the university. The records from classes have syllabi and material from the classes that Hartford taught at the university. The records from the DSA Strategic Data Planning committee include agendas and meeting minutes, mainly from committee retreats. The records on the experience of women include a report published by the Office of the Vice President of Student Affairs, titled "Finding a Voice: Experiences of Women Students at the University of Michigan," as well as all the documentation associated with the various focus groups with women at the university which informed the creation of this report. The records of the First Year Experience Task Force span from its conception in early 1993 until the release of the report of the task force in 1996. The records are arranged into two components: Output of the task force (which contain associated memoranda and correspondence as well as the final report and bibliography) as well as Sources of the task force (which contain materials such as survey instruments, statements prepared for the task force and other university related materials which the Task Force used to pursue its findings.) The records on health benefits include information on proposed health benefits for students. The Leadership 2017 Program file is about a program proposed by academic affairs that taught leadership and how to better interact with students. The campus safety files include newspaper clippings, correspondence with parents and students, and various committee recommendations. The sexual orientation file contains articles and information relating to the housing division and gay/lesbian lifestyles. The files of surveys contain various surveys administered to students, including the results. The undergraduate education statement file has information on programs and statistics regarding undergraduate students. These records partially document Maureen Hartford's tenure as Vice President of Student Affairs and also touch upon Mary Ann Swain's interim position as Vice President of Student Affairs prior to that.
  - Topical Files
    - Campus Improvement
      - Infrastructure Renewal Plan, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Value Centered Management, 1994-1995 (Box 41)
      - WCBN-FM Radio, 1991-1992 (Box 41)
    - Classes
      - The Freshman Year Seminar, 1993 (Box 41)
      - Management of Student Affairs Seminar, 1995-1999 (Box 41)
      - Psychology Department, 1994-1997 (Box 41)
    - DSA Strategic Data Planning
      - Council Meeting Agendas, 2000-2003; 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Council Retreat, 2000-2004; 5 folders (Box 41)
      - Goal Implementation Team, 2002-2003 (Box 41)
      - Leadership Assembly, 2005 (Box 41)
    - Experiences of Women Students
      - Report, "Finding a Voice,", 1994 (Box 41)
      - Violence Against Women, 1995 (Box 41)
      - Women Focus Group Results, 1993-1994 (Box 41)
      - Women in Education, 1992-1993 (Box 41)
    - First Year Experience
      - Output of Task Force
        - Final Report and Bibliography, 1994 (Box 41)
        - Formation of Task Force, 1992-1993 (Box 41)
        - Memoranda and Minutes, 1993-1994; 3 folders (Box 41)
        - Report, 1994-1996 (Box 41)
      - Sources Used by Task Force
        - Admitted Student Questionnaire Plus, University of Michigan Highlights Report by College Board, 1992 (Box 41)
        - Alcohol, 1993; 2 folders (Box 41)
        - CIRP Freshman Survey, 1993 (Box 42)
        - Comparisons with Other Universities, 1992-1993 (Box 42)
        - Curricular Issues, 1992-1993 (Box 42)
        - Living-Learning Communities, 1992-1993 (Box 42)
        - Medical School Acceptance, 1992 (Box 42)
        - Mentorship Program, 1993 (Box 42)
        - Minority Orientation and Issues, 1993 (Box 42)
        - Surveys, 1991-1993 (Box 42)
    - Health Benefits
      - Collegiate Health Care, 1994 (Box 42)
      - Proposal for Student Benefits Plan, 1995 (Box 42)
      - Student Health Insurance Programmatic Review, 1995 (Box 42)
    - Leadership 2017 Program, 1994 (Box 42)
    - Safety on Campus
      - Correspondence Regarding SafeRide, 1994 (Box 42)
      - Responses to President Duderstadt's Letter on Student Safety, 1990 (Box 42)
      - Safe Celebration Task Force, 1992 (Box 42)
      - Safety on Medical Campus, 1993 (Box 42)
      - Teargassing Incident on South University, 1991-1992 (Box 42)
      - University of Michigan Police Grievance Committee, 1992 (Box 42)
    - Sexual Orientation, 1993-1997 (Box 42)
    - Surveys
      - Compensation Survey, 1996 (Box 42)
      - Cooperative Institutional Research Program (CIRP), 1993-1996; 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Graduate/Professional Student Survey, 1995 (Box 42)
      - Student Activities Fee Survey, 1994-1995; 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Survey of Freshman Admits (SOFA), 1992-1993; 3 folders (Box 42)
      - Survey of Undergraduate Students, 1997 (Box 42)
    - Undergraduate Education Statement, 1990-1991 (Box 42)